<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                 -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Abstract Algebra: Theory and Applications   -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2010-2014  Robert A. Beezer     -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.  -->

<exercises>
	<title>Sage Exercises</title>

	<introduction>
		<p>These exercises are about becoming comfortable working with groups in Sage.</p>
	</introduction>

	<exercise number="1">
		<statement>
			<p>Create the groups <c>CyclicPermutationGroup(8)</c> and <c>DihedralGroup(4)</c> and give the two groups names of your choosing.  We will understand these constructions better shortly, but for now just understand that they are both groups.</p>
		</statement>
		<sage />
	</exercise>

	<exercise number="2">
		<statement>
			<p>Check that the groups have the same size with the <c>.order()</c> method.  Determine which is abelian, and which is not, by using the <c>.is_abelian()</c> method.</p>
		</statement>
		<sage />
	</exercise>

	<exercise number="3">
		<statement>
			<p>Use the <c>.cayley_table()</c> method to create the Cayley table for each group.</p>
		</statement>
		<sage />
	</exercise>

	<exercise number="4">
		<statement>
			<p>Write a nicely formatted discussionidentifying differences between the two groups that are discernible in properties of their Cayley tables.  In other words, what is {\em different} about these two groups that you can <q>see</q> in the Cayley tables?  (In the Sage notebook, a Shift-click on a blue bar will bring up a mini-word-processor, and you can use use dollar signs to embed mathematics formatted using <tex /> syntax.)</p>
		</statement>
		<sage />
	</exercise>

	<exercise number="5">
		<statement>
			<p>For each group, use the <c>.subgroups()</c> method to locate a largest subgroup that is not the entire group, and then use the <c>.list()</c> method of the subgroup to get a list of elements (which you might save as <c>elts</c>).</p>

			<p>Now, <c>.cayley_table(elements=elts)</c> for the original group will produce the Cayley table of the subgroup.  What properties of this table would you check to see if the output is correct?</p>
		</statement>
		<sage />
	</exercise>

	<exercise number="6">
		<statement>
			<p>The <c>.subgroup(elt_list)</c> method of the original group will create the smallest subgroup containing specified elements of the group, when given the elements as a list <c>elt_list</c>.  Discover the shortest list of elements necessary to recreate the subgroup you used in the previous exercise.  The equality comparison, <c>==</c>, can be used to test if two subgroups are equal.</p>
		</statement>
		<sage />
	</exercise>

</exercises>