<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                 -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Abstract Algebra: Theory and Applications   -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 1997-2014  Thomas W. Judson     -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.  -->

<!-- This file is part of the book                 -->
<!--                                               -->
<!--   Abstract Algebra: Theory and Applications   -->
<!--                                               -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2010-2014  Robert A. Beezer     -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions.  -->



</statement>
<sage />
</exercise>

<exercise number="1">
<statement>

Consider the polynomial <m>x^3-3x+4</m>.  Compute the most thorough factorization of this polynomial over each of the following fields:  (a) the finite field <m>{\mathbb Z}_5</m>, (b) a finite field with 125 elements, (c) the rationals, (d) the real numbers and (e) the complex numbers.  To do this, build the appropriate polynomial ring, and construct the polynomial as a member of this ring, and use the <c>.factor()</c> method.

</statement>
<sage />
</exercise>

<exercise number="2">
<statement>

<q>Conway polynomials</q> are irreducible polynomials over <m>{\mathbb Z}_p</m> that Sage (and other software) uses to build maximal ideals in polynomial rings, and thus quotient rings that are fields. Roughly speaking, they are <q>canonical</q> choices for each degree and each prime.  The command <c>conway_polynomial(p, n)</c> will return a database entry that is an irreducible polynomial of degree <m>n</m> over <m>{\mathbb Z}_p</m>.

Execute the command <c>conway_polynomial(5, 4)</c> to obtain an allegedly irreducible polynomial of degree 4 over <m>{\mathbb Z}_5</m>:  <m>p = x^{4} + 4x^{2} + 4x + 2</m>.  First determine that p has no linear factors.  The only possibility left is that <c>p</c> factors as two quadratic polynomials over <m>{\mathbb Z}_5</m>.  Use a list comprehension with <em>three</em> <c>for</c> statements to create <em>every</em> possible quadratic polynomial over <m>{\mathbb Z}_5</m>.  Now use this list to create every possible product of two quadratic polynomials and check to see if <c>p</c> is in this list.

More on Conway polynomials is available at
\url{http://www.math.rwth-aachen.de/~Frank.Luebeck/data/ConwayPol/index.html}

</statement>
<sage />
</exercise>

<exercise number="3">
<statement>

Construct a finite field of order <m>729</m> as a quotient of a polynomial ring by a principal ideal generated with a Conway polynomial.

</statement>
<sage />
</exercise>

<exercise number="4">
<statement>

Define the polynomials <m>p = x^3 + 2x^2 + 2x + 4</m> and <m>q = x^4 + 2x^2</m> as polynomials with coefficients from the integers.  Compute <c>gcd(p, q)</c> and verify that the result divides both <c>p</c> and <c>q</c> (just form a fraction in Sage and see that it simplifies cleanly, or use the <c>.quo_rem()</c> method).

Proposition~\extref{poly:gcd_ther}{17.7}{existence of polynomial gcd} says there are polynomials <m>r(x)</m> and <m>s(x)</m> such that the greatest common divisor equals <m>r(x)p(x)+s(x)q(x)</m>, <em>if the coefficients come from a field</em>.  Since here we have two polynomials over the integers, investigate the results returned by Sage for the extended gcd, <c>xgcd(p, q)</c>.  In particular, show that the first result of the returned triple is a multiple of the gcd.  Then verify the <q>linear combination</q> property of the result.

</statement>
<sage />
</exercise>

<exercise number="5">
<statement>

For a polynomial ring over a field, every ideal is principal.  Begin with the ring of polynomials over the rationals.  Experiment with constructing ideals using two generators and then see that Sage converts the ideal to a principal ideal with a single generator.  (You can get this generator with the ideal method <c>.gen()</c>.)  Can you explain how this single generator is computed?

</statement>
<sage />
</exercise>
